Okay, so today's דף daf is ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, but we start
on ל"ו עמוד ב'. Lamed Vav Amud Bet. Again, happy חנוכה Chanukkah
to everybody.
We are in the middle of a discussion about trusting a כהן
Kohen to say that this בכור Bechor was given with a מום
mum from ישראל. Yisrael. Now, the גמרא Gemara says, the משנה Mishnah
says you trust a כהן Kohen to say that the מום mum
was determined by a חכם Chacham to be a real מום, mum,
but that could simply be because, as we've said, even though he
might transgress making a מום mum in a בכור, Bechor, he is
not going to want to eat קדשים בחוץ. Kodshim bachutz. That's why
he bothers making the מום. mum. So he wants to make sure
it's a real מום. mum. So he's not suspect of lying whether
it is a מום. mum. He is suspect about lying about how
it got there. So the point in the גמרא Gemara was that
if he claims that he got it from a particular ישראל, Yisrael,
we believe him because we can always check up his story. Okay,
and that's the question: do you believe somebody if their story can
be checked or not? And the גמרא Gemara has been debating that.
What about cases where we don't trust the חכם? Chacham?
You mean like a
non-כהן? Kohen? Well, but just a סתם ישראל? stam Yisrael? I mean,
no, as a general rule I pointed out the other day that
even normally when somebody has a vested interest, according to הלכה, Halacha,
if I'm running a restaurant, you can trust me to say that
everything is כשר kosher even though I have a financial interest. So,
it's only because here
clearly they assessed the situation and they decided that there was a
particular problem here. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir goes so far as
to be suspect the entire class of כהנים. Kohanim. We only say
no, no, no, only if it directly affects you. You yourself, not
even your family members and so on. But the point is that
everything here is an exception. As a general
rule when it comes to איסור והיתר, issur ve-heter, when it comes
to business, we don't trust
people. I don't mean that fully, but I mean if somebody makes
a claim let's say in a court case in a civil case,
we don't assume people are telling the
truth. But when it comes to
איסור והיתר, issur ve-heter, whether it's giving a פסק psak about something
or whether it's about making a claim about the status of something,
the general rule is we believe. Now, that being said, I should
say, we did have a גמרא Gemara before that said about your
specific question about the sages, that a חכם Chacham is not believed
to give a ruling about his own בכור Bechor whether it's genuinely
a מום. mum. He's not believed, even if he's trying, maybe you
say not that he would necessarily intentionally lie but he can't be
objective and so on. And then it says there are other cases
where you can rule on your own things, on your own תרומה
וטהרה. Terumah ve-taharah. And the question came from that גמרא, Gemara, what
is the general rule? Is there a general rule that the חכם
Chacham can rule for things that affect him or not? And some
say the general rule is certainly if something starts with a חזקת
איסור, chazakas issur, starts with knowing that it's forbidden and you need
something positive to make it permissible like the case of a בכור,
Bechor, it started being forbidden and you needed a מום, mum, that
the general rule is that somebody cannot rule for himself. You need
to get somebody else, there's a concern about your ability to be
fully objective.
Others say no, the general rule is yes and again בכור Bechor
is the exception. So there is somewhat of a question about that
issue about giving rulings to yourself, but as a general rule, generally
we assume this גמרא Gemara is exceptions and not the rule. Okay,
so now we continue and the גמרא Gemara says like this. This
is the question about something that can be checked up, or עבידא
לגלויי. avida legiluia. So the גמרא Gemara picks up like this
where it says like this, אמר רבי
ירמיה בר אבא, Amar Rabbi Yirmiyahu bar Abba, three lines from the
top on ל"ו עמוד ב'. Lamed Vav Amud Bet. So we are
a good deal behind. Let's see. אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא מנא
ליה לרבי יהודה הא. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyahu bar Abba minalei le-Rabbi Yehuda
ha. Where did רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda get this idea that if
a כהן Kohen says ישראל Yisrael gave it to him, he's believed
because of what he calls because it can always be checked up?
האנא בגידל כביתי. Ha'ana be-Gidul kaveiti. Now there's a question exactly what
this phrase means. He says it means I taught it to either
somebody by the name of גידל Gidul or to a great person.
וגידל קבע בדידי ve-Gidul kava bedidi and גידל Gidul went ahead and
he taught it on his own or he taught it to רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but apparently it got messed up, meaning there was
a mistake of the transmission. Because here's how I originally taught this,
which in the end רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda heard via this גידל
Gidul through me, but he heard it wrong. Here's the way I
originally taught it. והכי אמר ליה, ve-hachi amar lei, and this is
what I said to גידל: Gidul: נאמן ישראל לומר בכור זה נתתי
לכהן במומו. ne'eman Yisrael lomar: bechor zeh natati le-Kohen be-mumo. That it's
not that a כהן Kohen can say I got this בכור Bechor
with the מום mum from the ישראל. Yisrael. The ישראל Yisrael can
say to an animal that's in a כהן's Kohen house, yeah, that
מום, mum, that was the animal I gave him and I gave
it to him when it originally had that מום. mum. Okay, so
the ישראל Yisrael can say he has absolutely no interest, no vested
interest in it. We've already said that the ישראל Yisrael is נאמן,
ne'eman, maybe even on his own בכור, Bechor, so certainly he's נאמן
ne'eman on a כהן's Kohen בכור. Bechor. And he says, yeah, I
know how it got that, I gave it to him. So גמרא
Gemara says so if that's true, מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashma lan?
So פשיטא, pshita, obviously, why would you even bother to teach that?
Look, צריכא, tzricha, here's why you needed to tell me: בקטן והגדיל,
be-katan ve-higdil, that he gave it to him when it was a
little lamb and now it's like a ram. So מהו דתימא, Mah
u-d'teima, I might think לא קים ליה בגוויה, lo kim lei begavah,
like maybe the ישראל Yisrael is misidentifying it, right? Maybe you gave
him a lamb and this is a ram and it's a different
animal. קמשמע לן Kamashmalan that we're not concerned about that. Okay, so
he said it really wasn't about אבידא לגלויי, avida l'igluyei, it was
a totally different story. Now I did wonder whether since in the
end the גמרא Gemara says that this is talking about קטן והגדיל,
katan ve-higdil, and he said I taught it to him בגידול, begidul,
that it maybe what the גמרא Gemara means here is that I
taught it to him about a case about something growing up and
not about the way he said it. That's not what רש"י Rashi
says. Anyway, okay, בסורא מתנו להא שמעתא, Besura matnu le-ha shemata, in
Sura they taught over this teaching like the second explanation, that it
was only about a ישראל Yisrael identifying his own animal or the
animal he gave. בפומבדיתא כלישנא קמא, Bepumbedita kelishna kama, in Pumbedita they
taught it the first way, that a כהן kohen is believed to
say a ישראל Yisrael gave this to him that way, and we
trust a כהן kohen in a matter that will anyway could or
easily be checked up. והלכתא אפילו כלישנא קמא, Vehilchata afilu kelishna kama,
we rule even like the first way, that you trust him even
though in general we suspect people about their own בכור. bechor. Here
if you can check it up, we trust him. And it's not
so obvious as I said the other day. People lie all the
times about things that can be checked up and a lot of
time people don't bother checking it up. People go on job interviews,
claim they graduate from Harvard and here are my references and the
people don't bother checking things up even though it's one phone call.
But the גמרא Gemara actually says that at least in this area
we believe on the basis of אבידא לגלויי, avida l'igluyei, and that's
important because it translates to other הלכה halacha areas as well where
things that can will naturally come to light or can be checked
up give more believability in certain cases.
Now we've also further limited the whole time where we don't believe
a כהן.
kohen. Right. Right. So now the case, the only case we don't
believe a בכור bechor is by כהן kohen about a בכור bechor
is number one, the כהן kohen himself who has the בכור. bechor.
We would believe his family members. We would believe him if we
did not have prior knowledge that it was a בכור bechor and
he's the one telling us it was a בכור. bechor. And now
we also believe him if he tells us that the ישראל Yisrael
gave it to him with a מום. mum. So right, the cases
we don't believe are being very limited. Yes.
This shows acceptance of different הלכה halacha practices in different communities.
It's not just אשכנז Ashkenaz and ספרד Sefard here. Oh yeah, neighboring.
Right. I mean exactly.
And yet they had different.
Yeah. And I mean that's well established in the גמרא. Gemara. A
famous phrase for that in the
גמרא Gemara is נהרא נהרא ופשטיה, nahara nahara u-pashtei, each river has
its tributaries. Thank you. So that different practices, there is diversity. Yeah,
the גמרא Gemara is well acknowledged that certainly. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
רפרם בפומבדיתא, Rafram be-Pumbedita, now we get a nice little story. רפרם
Rafram in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, now remember in פומבדיתא Pumbedita they taught like
that you believe somebody if it can be uncovered and revealed. So
רפרם Rafram was in פומבדיתא Pumbedita והוה ליה בכורא. ve-hava lei bechora.
He had a בכור bechor of his animals. ויהביה לכהן בלא מומא.
Ve-yahveih le-kohen belo muma. He gave it to a כהן kohen without
a blemish. And he gave it to him, he did what he
had to do. Now the כהן kohen has to wait for it
to get a blemish. אזל
שדא ביה מומא, Azal shada beih muma, so the כהן kohen went
and made a מום mum in it, like they're known to do.
יומא חד חלש בעיניה, Yoma chad chalash be-eineih, one day רפרם Rafram
had something bothering him in his eyes. So sort of like a
יצחק Yitzchak story. אתא לקמיה, Ata le-kameih, so the כהן kohen brought
this, he said now's my chance to get a ruling on this
because he's got his eyes are bad so he won't recognize it.
Of course, how bad could his eyes be if he had to
inspect the מום mum and determine that it was a מום? mum?
But okay, anyway, this כהן kohen now came to רפרם. Rafram. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, and he said to him, I need a ruling
on this
בכור. bechor. איך נפל ביה מומא? Eich nafal beih muma? בכור זה
נתן לי ישראל במומו. Bechor zeh natan li Yisrael be-mumo. So obviously,
so he said because when I got it, I got it with
its blemish. Okay, and we know that a כהן kohen is believed
if he makes that claim in פומבדיתא Pumbedita where you say the
matter can be revealed. All right, so again, it's pretty funny that
he thought he would get away with it because his eyes were
bad, but his eyes were good enough to inspect the מום mum
and determine that it was a מום. mum. Anyway, we'll see later
that in the next משנה Mishnah that even if it is an
obvious מום, mum, like it's missing a whole leg or something like
that, there still was a responsibility to get a ruling of a
חכם. chacham. So it could be that even with bad eyesight, if
it was a patently obvious blemish, but you still needed the חכם's
chacham ruling on it. Anyway, אפרסינהו לעיניה, Afrasinhu le-eineih, so he opened
his eyes or lifted up his eyelids.
חזייה בשיקרא, Chazyeih be-shikra, and he saw the lie. Now רש"י Rashi
reads the word בשיקרא be-shikra lie. He saw the lie. He saw
that it was actually the בכור bechor that he had given to
him. תוספות Tosafot actually says that the word בשיקרא be-shikra is actually
a word that means he recognized it. So תוספות Tosafot reads this
and he gives other examples of this. Doesn't mean שקר. sheker.
חזייה באשכרה, Chazyeih be-ashkara, probably I think the best part of the
root. He saw it and he recognized it is the way תוספות
Tosafot reads. Anyway, אמר ליה, Amar lei, לאו אנא הוא דיהבתי לך?
Lav ana hu de-yahavti lach? Hey, I gave it to you. Don't
try to pull the wool over my eyes as it were. I
gave it to you. I know that you must have put the
מום mum in it yourself. Now that was the story. So you
might think somebody that was attempted to have been fooled by that
way would say, ah, you see, people will lie even if it's
a matter that can be revealed. But the גמרא Gemara says, no,
ואפילו הכי לא חש לה למילתא, ve-afilu hachi lo chash lah le-milta,
even so רפרם Rafram was not concerned about that case. to generalize
and he said that was an exception. האי דחציף, hai de-chatzif, this
כהן Kohen was a חציפניק chatzifnik you know, this כהן Kohen was
brazen enough to try to get me, the same rabbi to rule
on the animal that I gave him. כולי עלמא לא חציפי, kulei
alma lo chatzifi, most people are not brazen and even if it's
a different sage, not that brazen and even if it's a different
sage, they're not they will be believed if they say they got
it from a from a from ישראל Yisrael because then the matter
can always be checked up.
Why did the כהן Kohen make a מום? mum?
Because he wanted to be able as we said, they're not suspect
for eating a בכור bechor outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
without a מום, mum, that's a כרת kares transgression, they are suspect
for making the מום mum in the בכור bechor so which allows
them to eat it out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Because as long as it doesn't have a מום mum he couldn't
eat it.
Once it has a מום mum you can eat it out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and if you do it's חייב כרת,
chayav kares, it's קדשים בחוץ. kodshim bachutz.
So he made the מום mum because he wanted to eat the
בכור, bechor, to shecht it. Yes, exactly.
And that's why they're suspect throughout here for making the מום.
mum. Is he allowed to do it?
No, that's why he's not allowed to do it, but they would
they would do it anyway.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So ההוא סרוע דאתא לקמיה דרב אשי. hahu sarua de-asa lekamei de-Rav
Ashi. So there was an animal that had a was a סרוע,
sarua, different sized eyes, okay again, nothing that can be done by
a by you know, by human intervention. סרוע Sarua is a blemish?
Just just explaining, I swear I remember it was just one limb
bigger than the other, doesn't
have to be an eye. Okay, but fine, רש"י Rashi says it's
the case with the eye. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב
אשי Rav Ashi said, רב אשי Rav Ashi said, למאי דחייש ליה,
le-mai de-cheish lei, what do we have to worry about? אי כהן
הוא ישראל הוא, ei Kohen hu Yisrael hu, whether it's a כהן
Kohen or ישראל, Yisrael, הרי בכור מומו עמו. harei bechor mumo imo.
So
it comes with its blemish meaning this could not have been done
by human intervention, so there's nothing to be concerned about.
So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, so
רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ודילמא ישראל הוא, vedilma
Yisrael hu, maybe he's not a כהן, Kohen, maybe he's ישראל, Yisrael,
ואמר רב יהודה אין רואין בכור לישראל אלא אם כן כהן עמו.
ve-amar Rav Yehuda ein ro'in bechor le-Yisrael ela im ken Kohen imo.
You can't give a ruling to a ישראל Yisrael for his בכור
bechor that it's a blemish without the כהן Kohen there. Why? Because
as soon as he finds out it's a good blemish, so on
the one hand ישראלים Yisraelim are not suspect of making a מום
mum in a בכור. bechor. On the other hand, they are suspect
about something else. As soon as they get a ruling that it
is a blemish and if the כהן Kohen isn't around, then we're
suspect they'll just keep it for themselves. Right. אמר ליה אטי השתא,
amar lei hati hashta, one minute. What do we have to be
worried about? התם, hasam, האי דקדשים בחוץ לא אכיל, hi de-kodshim bachutz
lo achal,
ממונא דכהן חטפי. mamona de-Kohen chatafei. Normally what we would say is
that ישראל Yisrael like כהן Kohen won't eat קדשים בחוץ, kodshim bachutz,
everybody is going to be won't eat it without a מום, mum,
okay the כהן Kohen is suspect of putting the מום, mum, the
ישראל Yisrael is suspect that if there's not a כהן Kohen around,
he's going to keep it for himself. ממונא דכהן חטפי, mamona de-Kohen
chatafei, he is suspect of taking the כהן's Kohen property. הכא, hacha,
that's the normal concern. הכא מכדי, hacha michdi, let's take a look
in this case. ידע דהאי מומו פקוע. yada de-hai mumu paku. The
ישראל Yisrael knew, he didn't need your ruling, okay, it was one
it was clearly a case that was an blatantly obvious blemish. He
did not need your ruling, okay, מאי טעמא שבא קמיה רבנן, mai
taama she-va kamei rabbanan, so why did he bother bring it to
you for a ruling? משום כבודה דחכם, mishum kevoda de-chacham, because he
was showing his deference and respect to you even though it is
transparently a blemish. Now we're going to see in the next משנה
Mishnah that it really wasn't much of a choice, that actually the
הלכה halacha demands that even in an obvious blemish you show it
to a חכם. chacham. But the point is, he knew that he
knew that it was a blemish. So if his only concern was
he doesn't want to eat a בכור bechor without a blemish and
he's we said he's willing to steal from a כהן, Kohen, he
also wants to follow the other הלכה halacha of asking a חכם.
chacham. Why put yourself out in the public eye and raise suspicions
and raise questions? Keep it at home, it's an obvious blemish, eat
it. So the same way you're willing to steal, you're willing not
to show it to a חכם. chacham. At least you know it's
a blemish. The fact that he was willing to show it to
a חכם chacham and follow that הלכה halacha and also make people
aware that he had this animal, so then obviously he was not
going to keep it for himself. He put himself in the public
eye like that and it would have been known if he would
have kept it for himself. So כבודה דחכם לא עביד איסורא לא
עביד, kevoda de-chacham lo avid issura lo avid, he's not going to
transgress, you know,
not respecting the חכם, chacham, he's going to go ahead and steal
the animal? We're not concerned in that case. So yes, because it
was an obvious מום mum and the there was no question that
he could have eaten it outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right,
the only the only thing was a הלכה halacha of respecting the
the חכם chacham to show it to him. So if you're going
to be so careful about that, we're not concerned that you're going
to be stealing. If he wanted to steal, he would have kept
it at home.
Exactly. So when it says אין רואין בכור לישראל אלא אם כן
כהן עמו, ein ro'in bechor le-Yisrael ela im ken Kohen imo, that's
for not obvious מומים. mumim.
Right, exactly. Okay.
So now we go over because they were concerned he's going to
actually keep it at home.
Exactly. And then he had to bring it to the חכם chacham
if it wasn't an obvious מום mum because then he wouldn't know
that he could eat it out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So because it is an obvious מום, mum, then as long as
he brings it to the חכם chacham he doesn't need any כהן.
Kohen.
Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now the next משנה. Mishnah. Although we've been
talking about this about a בכור, bechor, הכל נאמנים על מומי מעשר.
hakol ne'emanim al mumei ma'aser. Everybody is trusted about blemishes by מעשר
ma'aser which actually has the same הלכה halacha that you can't eat
it outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash without a מום. mum. So
מאי טעמא, mai taama, why is it any different? You have the
same type of incentive. But the answer is דאי בעי שדי ביה
מומא מעיקרא De-i ba'ei shadi bei muma me'ikara because you could have
put a blemish before it became מעשר. Ma'aser. So if you wanted
to cheat, you would have cheated without violating. So the גמרא Gemara
says מי ידע הי נפק? Mi yada hai nafak? How do you
know which one is going to come out tenth? וכי תימא מפיק
ליה ברישא עשרה, Ve-chi teima mapik lei be-reisha asara, maybe you're going
to sort of manipulate it so that the one you made the
מום mum in comes out as the tenth? לא יבקר בין טוב
לרע אמר רחמנא, Lo yivaker bein tov le-ra amar Rachmana, you cannot
manipulate it. Thank you. So there's how could you have done it
legitimately? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא דאי בעי שדי ביה מומא
בכל עדריה. Ela de-i ba'ei shadi bei muma be-chol edrei. He could
have put a blemish in his entire flock. And that's the phrase
the גמרא Gemara used before. So basically we believe people about מעשר
Ma'aser because מעשר Ma'aser is מעשר Ma'aser is something that if you
wanted to cheat, if you wanted to, you know, you could cheat
without violating. So therefore we're not going to suspect you about cheating
with violation. Even though it's a little far-fetched, that's enough of a
reason to say that we're not going to suspect you for doing
איסורים. issurim. Okay. Now we get back to בכור. Bechor.
Wait, you didn't say anything about the could you have done it
also when it's still in the...
Yeah, but that's true about בכור Bechor as well and we don't
use that as an excuse, so presumably that was too hard to
assume that people would go to that effort. Okay. בכור שנפגם... Bechor
she-nifgam... now we get to the issue of having to show it
to a חכם. Chacham. בכור שנסמית עינו ושנגדעה ידו ושנשברה רגלו הרי
זה ישחט על פי ג' בני כנסת. Bechor she-nismis eino ve-shenigde'a yado
ve-shenishbera raglo harei ze yishachet al pi gimel benei kenesset. So here
you have a case where it has patently obvious blemish. There's no
question that it's a blemish. It's blinded in the eye, presumably the
eye is poked out, presumably its arm is cut off, its leg
is broken. You don't need anybody but, you know, a kindergarten kid
could tell you that that's a מום. mum. Nevertheless, there's a separate
הלכה halacha that you need to get a ruling from a חכם.
Chacham. Now, normally we demand a מומחה, mumche, an expert. Here, because
it is so obvious, we don't demand a מומחה, mumche, but we
demand a בית דין. Beis Din. But it could be three random
people. שלשה מבני כנסת Shelosha mi-benei kenesset means you go to שול,
shul, you חאפ chap three people, it doesn't matter who they are,
you get a ruling. Okay, men, right. Thank you, it does matter
that they're men, right, exactly.
Thank you, thank you for that, Rivka. Keeping me honest.
Could the מומחה mumche be a woman?
That's an interesting question. I'll talk about that. I don't know. I
have to look into
that. Broken leg. Yeah, I mean if it will heal, then not,
then it's a מום עובר. mum over. I don't know how much
that they were able to put, you know, really set the bones
and whatever. That's a good question, like maybe it could heal. Right,
maybe it could heal. Yeah, so I don't know, I don't know
exactly. But don't they like, isn't that like what they shoot a
horse when it breaks its leg? So however it, I don't know,
anyway, maybe it'll heal but it can't do work again. I don't
know. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, okay, so anyway,
so that's the point that even... so look at the structure that
חז"ל Chazal have created on top of בכור. Bechor. They first thing
they've said is we need to prove that it is how it
got the מום. mum. And you know, there needs to be testimony,
who do you believe, who don't you believe, etc. It needs to
be, we need to know that you didn't make the מום mum
yourself. And if we don't have good evidence that you didn't make
the מום mum yourself, then you know, you can't eat it because
we suspect you of making the מום mum yourself. After we've now
said we need that evidence, right, it's almost like עדות eidus and
now there's a דין. din. Now to give a, now we need
to give a ruling on the בכור, Bechor, right, and decide that
it is a blemish and that needs either a מומחה mumche or
if you don't need a מומחה, mumche, you don't need expertise, at
least you need a בית דין. Beis Din. Now, רבי יוסי אומר
אפילו יש שם כ"ג אינו
נשחט אלא על פי מומחה. Rabbi Yossi omer afilu yesh sham chaf-gimel
eino nishchat ela al pi mumche.
You always need an expert because maybe you don't want to ever
think that oh, well once I can go to a בית דין
Beis Din for this, I can go to a בית דין Beis
Din even if it's a more complicated case. You want to make
it clear that you always need the ruling of an expert. Now,
just to show you how interest, you know, what's going on here,
notice כ"ג chaf-gimel is a concept taken from בית דין, Beis Din,
right? 23 is a בית דין Beis Din that can deal with
capital cases. And what we're really doing is we're sort of, as
I said, laying over a whole phenomenon that deals with כהנים Kohanim
and מתנות כהונה, matnos kehuna, a whole type of sort of rabbinic
עדות eidus בית דין Beis Din structure. Even the concept of מומחה
mumche is a concept that we have from בית דין, Beis Din,
right? There's an idea in the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin whether
a יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche, an individual who's an expert, can rule
even without three. So that's also like a בית דין Beis Din
structure. But it is a little bit stranger because normally this is
the area of כהנים Kohanim that we're creating this structure on top.
So just to show how like, you know, a little strange it
is, somebody showed me the most absurd but in some way understandable
mistranslation in Soncino. Soncino translates this line in the משנה, Mishna, אפילו
יש שם כ"ג, afilu yesh sham chaf-gimel, אפילו יש שם כהן גדול.
afilu yesh sham Kohen Gadol.
So what? But because we're dealing with an area of כהנים Kohanim
and we're laying over it this whole בית דין Beis Din structure,
so they misread כ"ג chaf-gimel as כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Anyway, let's
take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. So you always need
the ruling of a מומחה mumche and if it's an obvious one
you can use a normal בית דין Beis Din according to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, but you do need a ruling. רב שמלאי
ורב יהודה נשיאה. Rav Simlai ve-Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah. רב שמלאי בר יהודה
נשיאה, Rav Simlai bar Yehuda Nesia, which is the grandson of רב
יהודה נשיא, Rav Yehuda Nasi, not to be
confused, תרווייהו משמיה דרב יהושע בן לוי אמרי, traveihu mishmeih deRav Yehoshua
ben Levi amri, they both say in the name of רב יהושע
בן לוי, Rav Yehoshua ben Levi, ואמרי לה, v'amri lei, and some
say ואמרי לה v'amri lei רב שמלאי ורב יהושע בן לוי תרווייהו
משום יהודה נשיאה אמרי. Rav Simlai v'Rav Yehoshua ben Levi traveihu mishum
Yehuda Nesia amri. So okay, it's A and B said in the
name of A and C said in the name of B. Okay,
just who said in the name of who. Anyways, here's what they
said: התרת בכור בחוץ לארץ על פי שלשה בני כנסת. hataras bechor
b'chutz la'aretz al pi shlosha bnei kneses. That when you're מתיר matir
the בכור bechor in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
you need a בית דין. Beis Din. Okay. אמר רבא: Amar Rava:
ובמומין מובהקין, u'v'mumin mufakin, only like obvious מומין. מובהקין mumin mufakin means
like it's obvious, you don't it doesn't need any discretion, any judgment,
which is essentially the point of our משנה. mishna. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara says: מאי קמשמע לן? mai k'mashma lan? What's he
saying that you're limiting it to מומין mumin. מובהקין mufakin then that's
our משנה. mishna. תנינא, Tanina, we learned our משנה: mishna: בכור שניסמית
עינו ושניקטעה ידו ונשברה רגלו הרי זה ישחט על פי ג' בני
כנסת. bechor shenispetnu u'shnisatei yado v'nishbar raglo, harei zeh yishachet al pi
gimmel bnei kneses. So you alright,
but he still added חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, it seems like he
was saying something different. So our משנה mishna says that. So גמרא
Gemara says no. אי ממתניתין הוה אמינא, Ee mi'matnisin hava amina, if
from our משנה mishna I would have said בחוץ
לארץ אפילו מומין שאין מובהקין. b'chutz la'aretz afilu mumin she'ein mufakin. And
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz even non-expert מומין, mumin, even non-evident
מומין. mumin. האי דקתני מובהקין, Hai dikatani mufakin, so why does our
משנה mishna speak about evident מומין? mumin? להודיע כוחו דרבי יוסי, L'odiah
kocho d'Rabbi Yosi, to tell you that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi even
in that case requires a מומחה. mumcheh. But so that but maybe
the חכמים, hachamim, maybe they allow a בית דין Beis Din even
without an obvious מום, mum, and certainly and maybe they allow it
and maybe in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz in particular. קמשמע לן K'mashma
lan not that way. Now why is חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz different
is interesting. We'll see later that you didn't bring the בכור bechor
from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but that might have been a rabbinic
issue and you know and there still would be a problem of
קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz if you didn't need a מום. mum. So
it's not if it didn't have a מום. mum. So it's not
exactly clear why we would have been more lenient by חוץ לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. If anything, תוספות Tosafos says that we might have been
more strict. We might have wanted to say that if we allow
it at a time when there is a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and we allow it in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, then we'll come
to allow it even in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash purposes and maybe we would be concerned that that would,
you know, lead to a slippery slope. Anyway, it's not so clear
why I would have thought חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz was different, but
the גמרא Gemara does emphasize, doesn't really fully explore that. What it
does emphasize is is that the משנה mishna when it says evident
מומין mumin is דוקא, davka, that only evident מומין mumin you can
have a בית דין. Beis Din. If it's not evident, you need
a מומחה. mumcheh. And whether it's in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, whatever the case might be, you always you
always only when it's evident you need a בית דין, Beis Din,
but but when it even when it's evident you still do need
a ruling. Okay, so two points: you always need a ruling, whether
evident or not, but when it is evident, then you can get
by with a בית דין Beis Din without an expert. Now the
גמרא Gemara continues: אמר רב יהודה אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba, ספק משמיה דרב ספק משמיה
דשמואל. safek mishmei d'Rav safek mishmei d'Shmuel. So now רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said in the name of רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmeya
bar Abba question whether it originated in רב Rav or שמואל, Shmuel,
the following statement: ג' מתירין את הבכור במקום שאין מומחה. gimmel matirin
es habechor b'makom she'ein mumcheh. You can use a בית דין Beis
Din if you don't have a מומחה. mumcheh. All right. So the
question is right, is it מובהק mufak or not מובהק? mufak? So
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says: מאי קמשמע לן?
mai k'mashma lan? What are you telling me? תנינא, Tanina, it's our
משנה: mishna: הרי זה ישחט על פי ג' בני כנסת. harei zeh
yishachet al pi gimmel bnei kneses. You can use just a normal
בית דין. Beis Din. So the גמרא Gemara says no: אי ממתניתין
הוה אמינא Ee mi'matnisin hava amina אפילו במקום מומחה. afilu b'makom mumcheh.
Maybe in our משנה mishna I would have said that even if
there's a מומחה mumcheh available. קמשמע לן: K'mashma lan: במקום שאין מומחה,
b'makom she'ein mumcheh, במקום שיש מומחה לא. b'makom she'yesh mumcheh lo.
That no, our משנה mishna only allows a בית דין Beis Din
if there's no מומחה mumcheh available. So now right, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't suspect for a minute that you would allow a non-מומחה mumcheh
by a difficult case. Okay, so if you're going to allow three
laypeople, three people that are really ignorant, then you're then it's just
a formality, it can only be by an evident one. But even
there, this is like a halfway concession to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
in the משנה. mishna. Even when it's evident and we allow a
בית דין, Beis Din, that's only if there's no מומחה mumcheh available.
But if there's a מומחה mumcheh readily available, you have to go
to the מומחה. mumcheh. Again, presumably because you want to underscore, you
certainly don't want to undermine the role of the מומחה mumcheh and
you don't want people going to a בית דין Beis Din when
it really needs a מומחה. mumcheh. So this is a halfway concession
to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. If there's a מומחה mumcheh available, you
have to go to the מומחה. mumcheh. Now, I do want to
say a second about what exactly is a מומחה mumcheh and showing
the question about how much is this borrowing a בית דין Beis
Din model. If you take a look at תוספות: Tosafos: במקום שיש
מומחה לא, b'makom she'yesh mumcheh lo, תוספות Tosafos says: לאו דוקא lav
davka
מומחה, mumcheh, now question is how you read this גרסא girsa שימחו
בית דין, she'imchu beis din, but also there's a question in the
if the side גרסא girsa where it says חזיין hartzayan
שסמכוהו ברבי. she'samchuha b'Rebbi. Okay, meaning not a מומחה mumcheh that got
the סמיכה semicha that goes back to משה רבנו, Moshe Rabbeinu, that
is a type of a סמיכה semicha that allows you to be
on a בית דין Beis Din like a capital case and so
on, that's not the type of מומחה mumcheh we're talking about, but
he says but really what we're talking about is he goes on
basically saying that somebody that is expert. And he brings proof that
he brings proof that the people that ruled on בכורים bechors were
not people that actually had real
סמיכה, semicha, etc., etc. And then he goes on. And the רמב"ם
Rambam says more like... It’s the same thing that we’re talking about
somebody that has real expertise, maybe somebody the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* also
adds, and this depends on the גרסא girsa *Girsa* in תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos* if this is also a תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* that’s rejected, you
know the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* about סמיכה *Smicha* is the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* also, you know, יורה יורה yoreh yoreh *Yoreh Yoreh* is about
people getting a license from the נשיא *Nasi* and from the political
authority to have their role as being a judge. So יורה *Yoreh*,
can he give rulings in איסור Issur, והיתר *Issur V’Heter*, יורה *Yoreh*
he can. ידין *Yadin*, can he sit on a בית דין beit
din. *Beis Din*, ידין *Yadin*. And then the third one is יתיר
בכורות bechorot, *Yatir Bechoros*. This is fascinating again how the idea of
בכור bechor *Bechor* got pulled into the system of בית דין beit
din *Beis Din*. So right, there’s a idea of מומחה mumcha *Mumche*,
there’s an idea of three, even twenty-three was thrown out, and now
it’s like on the level of degrees of authorization to rule and
בכור’ס *Bechor’s* the most complicated and is at the top of that
level. So again, I don’t know what to fully do with this
but again what we’ve really been seeing is first you need עדות
*Edus* how it got, you know, how it got the מום mum
*Mum*, then you need a ruling and the ruling is being sort
of put in this entire בית דין beit din, *Beis Din* structure.
So that’s the idea of מומחה *Mumche* to the point that תוספות
Tosafot *Tosfos* has to say that you don’t actually need real סמיכה
*Smicha*, the type of סמיכה *Smicha* that goes back to משה רבינו
*Moshe Rabbeinu*.
Okay, so can a woman be a מומחה *Mumche*?
Yeah, so that’s an interesting question, right, that Michael asked, and I
don’t know if that’s discussed, right, but that’s an exact good case
of that. If it’s really just about giving a ruling and expertise
and it’s not about sitting into the בית דין beit din. *Beis
Din* structure and בית דין beit din. *Beis Din* is like an
alternative, either you need an expert ruling, if you can’t get an
expert ruling, we’ll have a formality with a בית דין beit din
*Beis Din*. But that the expert ruling is really its own track
of a normal ruling of איסור והיתר *Issur V’Heter*, then a woman
could do it, right? A woman who knows, a woman could פסקן
הלכה halacha *Pasken Halacha*, there’s no problem with that. So that would
be true. But if the concept of מומחה *Mumche* is built on
the בית דין beit din *Beis Din* concept of מומחה *Mumche*, right,
then it would exclude women. So that’s an excellent test case. And
that’s exactly the question going on here which is the importing of
a whole בית דין *Beis Din* structure.
Are women included in בני הכנסת *Bnei HaKnesses*?
That I would assume is definitely not because again if the idea
of three is a בית דין *Beis Din* concept. Well, it is
true, there is a position in תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* that a woman
could be on a בית דין *Beis Din*, right? That even if
a woman can’t be an עד *Ed* she can be on a
בית דין *Beis Din*. But assuming like the consensus not, then the
I would assume three definitely not. I think מומחה *Mumche* is the
interesting question. So had you seen it anywhere? I don’t know, I’d
have to look, but whether מומחה *Mumche*, not so many people are
bothering writing a lot of literature on being מומחה *Mumche* about בכור
Bechor. *Bechor*. Okay, but anyway, all right, so let’s take a look.
But what is clear here is again that bringing together of that
entire סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* model. That’ll be a contribution? Exactly. Okay, so now
we go on. So אמר רב Rav חייא בר עמרם *Amar Rav
Chiya bar Amram*, so now we’ve said that if a מומחה *Mumche*
is available you have to go there. אמר רב Rav חייא בר
עמרם *Amar Rav Chiya bar Amram*, ג' מתירין את הבכור במקום שאין
מומחה *Gimel matirin es habechor bemakom she’ein mumche*. Three people can allow
a בכור bechor, *Bechor* if there’s not a מומחה *Mumche* around. Fine,
that’s our משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, just making it again presumably that it’s
an evident thing that you don’t need their expertise. ג' מתירין את
הנדר במקום שאין חכם chacham, *Gimel matirin es haneder bemakom she’ein chacham*.
And also do התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim, *Hataras Nedarim* like we do
on ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*, right, you can do it your... you’re
supposed to have a מומחה *Mumche* but if again if you don’t
have a מומחה *Mumche* then you can, then or you’re allowed to
do it by a single מומחה *Mumche*, supposed to or allowed to,
a little one or the other anyway, and
but if you don’t then you can go to a בית דין
*Beis Din*. ג' מתירין את הבכור במקום שאין מומחה לאפוקי מדברי רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Gimel matirin es habechor bemakom she’ein mumche l’afukei midivrei
Rabbi Yosef*. Here’s what Michael wanted to say originally but that why
are we bothering saying that you don’t need an expert? Because to
reject רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosef* who says you do need
a מומחה *Mumche*. So maybe if it’s only if there’s no מומחה
*Mumche* available but at least you’re able to go forward that’s you
can do it with three without a מומחה *Mumche*. שלשה מפירין את
הנדר *Shlosha mafirin es haneder*, it really should be מתירין *matirin*, הפרה
*hafara* is what the בעל *ba'al* does, but תוספות *Tosfos* discusses the
use of the word. Anyway, a בית דין *Beis Din* can be
מתיר matir נדרים *matir nedarim* במקום שאין חכם chacham *bemakom she’ein chacham*.
That even and without a חכם chacham *chacham*, if a חכם chacham,
*chacham* is not available you’re allowed to go to three without a
חכם chacham *chacham*. לאפוקי מדרבי יהודה *L’afukei mid’Rabbi Yehuda*.
To exclude רבי יהודה’ס *Rabbi Yehuda’s* position. תניא התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim.
בג' *Tanya hataras nedarim b’gimel*. You can use three to do התרת
*hataras*, it really means התרה *hatara*, התרת נדרים *hataras nedarim*. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda אומר אחד מהם חכם chacham *Rabbi Yehuda omer echad mehem
chacham*. Nope, you actually you actually need a sage even if you
have a בית דין *Beis Din* you cannot do it without a
sage, you always need his presence.
So he’s saying you need three, one of whom...
Yes, one of them is, or it sounds like. And that’s תוספות
*Tosfos* tries to figure that out because if you have a חכם
chacham *chacham* nobody says you need a בית דין *Beis Din*. So
תוספות *Tosfos* said maybe we’re talking about a middle-level חכם chacham *chacham*.
He’s not a חכם chacham *chacham* enough to be מתיר נדר matir
neder *matir neder* by himself but he has to be a certain
חכם chacham *chacham* to be on the בית דין *Beis Din*.
You mean both,
three and one of which is... He is saying you need both,
but תוספות *Tosfos* says that the only way תוספות *Tosfos* is able
to make sense of that is if we’re not talking about the
level of חכם chacham *chacham* that could be מתיר נדר matir neder,
*matir neder* by himself.
What’s that mean? That’s what he’s saying.
I know, I’m just telling you, תוספות *Tosfos* assumes that nobody argues
on that. Okay, so on the one hand there are those that
say you always need a חכם chacham *chacham*, we are saying we
don’t say that you can ignore the חכם chacham. *chacham* or the
מומחה *Mumche* if they’re available, we sort of meet רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi *Rabbi Yosef* halfway, but if they’re not available then you can
go forward. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just explores this התרת
נדרים *hataras nedarim*, במקום שאין חכם chacham. כגון מן *bemakom she’ein chacham
k’gon man*? Who would be a חכם Chacham *chacham* that we are
talking about? So אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman כגון אנא *Amar Rav
Nachman k’gon ana*. Like me, for example. Okay,
so what’s the point of that? So let’s finish this and I’ll
just say what תוספות *Tosfos*... says about this. So רבי יהודה אומר
אחד מהם חכם, Chacham so one of them have to be a
חכם, Chacham so of the בית דין. מכלל הנך כולהו? mikhlal hanakh
kulu? The other people can like know nothing? So how can they
be part of the whole process? I mean it's one thing by
a בכור bechor that if it's patently obvious a broken leg, yes
you could know nothing and still say yeah that's a broken leg.
Okay, but for התרת נדרים, how could they at all be part
of the process if they don't know anything? So אמר רבינא דמסתברא
ליה וסבר. Amar Ravina dimstavra lei vesavar. No, they have to be
intelligent enough that you can explain to them what's going on and
they get it. So look what we're going to do, the person
said this based on this, we're going to decide this. And the
חכם Chacham says that to the other people on the בית דין
so that they can be part of the process. Now תוספות says
what's going on here, the best read תוספות has of this גמרא.
Gemara Why do you assume just because it said not חכם Chacham
it could be somebody that knows nothing? Why do you go to?
So that's why תוספות says what's going on here is we're assuming
a mid-level חכם, Chacham, which is we're not assuming חכם Chacham at
the level that it could be מתיר נדר by himself, that רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi would not deny that a חכם Chacham, can do
it by himself. So if you need a חכם chacham on a
בית דין, what's this hybrid? So that's why the גמרא Gemara says
what type of a חכם are you talking about? So if רב
נחמן Rav Nachman said oh like me, which doesn't mean he's a
mid-level חכם in terms of intelligence or knowledge, but somehow not in
a position to be מתיר נדר, but enough to you know bring
some intelligent conversation into the בית דין. So then the גמרא Gemara
says oh but if we're talking that you need a mid-level חכם
then it would suggest the other people know zero and that's why
it had to clarify what is the status of the other people
that they were able to at least be able to be brought
in to be part of the process. Okay.
רב Rav נחמן saying he is sort of a mid-level חכם
for the purposes of התרת נדרים. That's sort of the way תוספות
reads it although that is strange. Okay anyway fine fine moving on.
רבי יוסי אומר אפילו יש שם Rabbi Yossi omer afilu yesh sham
not כהן גדול kohen gadol but כ"ג, kaf gimmel, twenty-three. אמר רב
חננאל אמר רב Amar Rav Chananel amar Rav אין הלכה כרבי יוסי.
ein halacha keRabbi Yossi. We don't rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
which is what we've just been saying. פשיטא Peshita obviously. יחיד ורבים
הלכה כרבים. Yachid verabbim halacha kerabbim.
We always go like the majority. No מהו דתימא mahu d'teima נימוקו
עמו, nimuko imo, I might say that sometimes we particularly rule like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi because we say his sort of reason is
with him, that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. you know רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi, normally has very reasoned positions. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that we
don't say it here. So now the גמרא Gemara says תפשוט מהא
דהך קמייתא משמיה דשמואל איתמר. tipshot mei-ha de-hach kamaisa mishmei de-Shmuel itmar.
So now we're saying that רב Rav said we rule like רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi if you remember but we rule against רבי יוסי.
Before we had a statement and it wasn't clear whether it was
originated in רב Rav? or שמואל Shmuel that you can use a
בית דין. So now the גמרא Gemara says oh so the earlier
statement must have been שמואל Shmuel or else רב would have been
repeating
himself. דאי משמיה דרב Di-im mishmei de-Rav if that earlier statement was
רב תרתי למה לי? tarti lama li? Why before did he say
you can use a בית דין and here he says we don't
rule like רבי יוסי, why repeat yourself? גמרא Gemara says no חדא
מכלל דחברתה איתמר. chada mikhlal de-chaverteih itmar. He didn't say both. He
could have said one and we and we rephrased it as the
second one. He really said one but you know it was said
over you know in a different way so it sounds like two
separate statements.
Okay couple questions I know we're a little bit over. Yes. So
you've many times explained how
people published things by putting their imprimatur on it. So what's this
idea that that we manufactured this additional statement of רב?
Yeah that's a that is a very good question you know
yeah
I don't know I mean okay but second question.
We have rules of יחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים yachid verabbim halacha kerabbim
but we also have many many exceptions don't we? Yes. So I'm
a little why did the גמרא Gemara take it for granted that
this יחיד ורבים yachid verabbim
overrode the rule of רבי יוסי נימוקו עמו? Rabbi Yossi nimuko imo?
Yeah okay another good question which I don't have a good answer
to other than that yes the rules sort of contradict themselves. I'll
give you one great example that the rules contradict themselves. One הלכה
is הלכתא כבתראי, hilkheta ke-vatraei, we always go like the later opinion
and the other position is אין הלכה כתלמיד במקום הרב. ein halacha
ke-talmid bimkom harav. So I mean they don't always contradict themselves but
anyway there is those those contradictions are never really systematized. But it's
still a good question that even though it's not systematized why did
the גמרא Gemara, start by saying פשיטא? peshita? Right? I mean okay
it's not systematized but it's still not פשיטא peshita the other way.
All right two very good questions. Let's now move on. השוחט את
הבכור ונודע שלא הראהו. Hashocheit et habechor venoda she-lo herahu. So here
is ex we've already decided that if we don't have a good
evidence that it got the מום mum by itself you can't eat
it בדיעבד bediavad and you have to bury it. Let's say now
right we've got the two levels of that you have to pass
through. One is to prove it got it by itself and the
next is to get a ruling from a חכם even or a
בית דין even from a patently obvious one. Let's say it is
clear it got it by itself but then you didn't show it
to a חכם. What's the story now? Okay השוחט את הבכור ונודע
שלא הראהו, hashocheit et habechor venoda she-lo herahu, it was known that
you did not show it to a חכם. So מה שאכלו אכלו
ויחזיר להם הדמים. ma she-achlu achlu ve-yachazir lahem hadamim. So what apparently
the case here is is that the כהן kohen if it's the
כהן kohen it's his own so fine did just bury the rest.
But now what he actually did is he sold the meat. Okay
and now what's the story about the people that bought it from
him and they weren't allowed and they don't know whether it actually
had a מום Mum or not? So he says what they ate
they ate you have to have a חכם rule on it. And
if a חכם didn't rule on it, you didn't...
Now, there is a question earlier in the גמרא Gemara can a
חכם
rule on it after the fact, after it's been שחט-ed shecht or
not. But if a חכם hasn't ruled on it, then it's considered,
you know, can't be eaten. Now the question I would say is,
what if, what if it's a case of a patently obvious מום
Mum, that a חכם didn't rule on, right? Where would we go
so far to demand, it could be a case where it was
a questionable מום, Mum okay? So it's not clear in this משנה
Mishnah where we assume it's אסור בדיעבד Asur B'diavad if it wasn't
shown to a חכם, would that even be the case of an
obvious מום Mum, or was a formality to show it to a
חכם or would it only be in a case of a non-obvious.
Okay, but either way, here you went ahead and sold it and
the assumption is that the meat is אסור. Asur. So how do
you make good on this? So מה שאכלו אכלו Ma She'achlu Achlu
what the people ate they ate, I mean, you know, they're not
going to be able to deal about that, they've eaten it. ויחזיר
להם את הדמים V'yachzir Lahem Et HaDamim and he has to give
them their money back because he didn't have any right to sell
it and therefore he didn't have any right to take their money.
So ומה שלא אכלו U'ma Shelo Achlu and what they didn't eat,
הבשר יקבר, HaBasar Yikaver, so, you know, bury the remaining meat. ויחזיר
להם את הדמים V'yachzir Lahem Et HaDamim and give them back the
money. So it's a little redundant. I mean, but fine, it might
be give them back the money for what they ate and give
them back the money for what they didn't eat. Okay, either way,
you didn't have a right to sell it. וכן השוחט את הפרה
ומכרה ונודע שהיא טריפה. V'chen HaShochet Et HaParah U'machrah V'noda Shehi Treifah.
Here's a more common case. A butcher sold a פרה, Parah, sold
the meat, and then it was discovered to have been a טריפה.
Treifah. Maybe he didn't even do anything wrong, maybe it was discovered
after the fact. I guess he could have checked better, but anyway.
מה שאכלו אכלו Ma She'achlu Achlu what the people ate they ate.
ומה שלא אכלו U'ma Shelo Achlu but what they didn't eat, הם
יחזירו לו את הבשר, Hem Yachziru Lo Et HaBasar, they don't bury
the meat because what can you do with טריפה Treifah meat? You
can give it to the dogs, make dog food. So give it
back to him. והוא יחזיר להם את הדמים V'hu Yachzir Lahem Et
HaDamim and he should give them back their money. They paid for
kosher meat, they give him back this טריפה Treifah meat and he
gives them back their money. If they want to buy dog food,
they'll buy it as dog food, but they have no obligation to
keep it and he reimburses them. Now, מכרו לעובדי כוכבים. Machru L'ovdei
Kochavim. Now, by the way, I should say, it's not exactly clear
from this משנה Mishnah if he gives them back the money for
the food that they ate. Because they actually, although they ate איסור,
they got the benefit of having a nice steak dinner.
And you know, so...
Right, and it could be that that's before it said it twice
because there he gives them back the money for even because since
it was אסור בהנאה Asur B'hana'ah and so on, he didn't have
a right to take any of their money. Here, he could have
sold it, but he could have sold it as dog food. So
maybe he doesn't have to give them back the money for what
they ate. That's what the משנה Mishnah sounds like a little bit,
but from the גמרא Gemara. and the רמב"ם or whatever, it seems
like they don't make that distinction, they don't read it that way
and they assume that even in the טריפה Treifah case, he gives
them back all their money. It was bought under false pretenses and
therefore he gives them back all their money. Exactly. Okay, now, מכרו
לעובדי כוכבים או הטילו לכלבים ישלמו דמי טריפה. Machru L'ovdei Kochavim O
Hitilu Laklavim Yeshalmu Demei Treifah. Now, if they actually didn't eat it,
but they treated it as dog food, they bought it as kosher
meat and without knowing they just decided to do the same thing
they would do with טריפה, Treifah, they gave it to their dog
or sold it to a non-Jew. So therefore, essentially they used it
as טריפה Treifah meat in that case, so they're entitled to get
back, he doesn't have to give them back all their money because
effectively they bought טריפה Treifah meat, so he would give them back
the difference between טריפה Treifah meat and kosher meat. Okay, because effectively
that's what it turned out that the purchase was as opposed to
a מקח טעות Mekach Ta'ut which was the first case. How do
you find out after the meat is sold it's טריפה, Treifah, right?
No, you looked at a lung and you saw that there was
a... You saw the knife, yeah, exactly. Okay, very, very quick question
just to make sure I understood this. So what we're saying is
this משנה Mishnah is potentially saying that even in a case where
it was a patently obvious מום, Mum. if it wasn't shown to
a חכם, we find him to such an extent that he may
have to redeem. Yeah, I don't know. No, I told you that
earlier. So if you don't know, it means it's a possibility, right?
So maybe, right. The משנה Mishnah is unclear whether the post-facto forbidding
of the meat would extend even to a case of an obvious
מום. Mum. Or even if they already ate. Right, right, right. Very
big. Yes, but that would be a sort of how חז"ל, Chazal,
what the structure... But that's why I would much rather read this
משנה mishnah to be talking about like a non-obvious מום. mum Okay,
but again, I just haven't checked. I'm sure that the ראשונים Rishonim
discuss it. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. המוכר בשר
לחברו ונמצא בשר בכור. HaMocher Basar L'chavero V'nimtza Basar Bechor. You sold
meat and then it was discovered, maybe you were innocent about it
and somehow you realized after the fact that it was a בכור.
bechor? או פירות ונמצאו טבלים, O Peirot V'nimtzu Tevalim, you sold fruit,
maybe you were a middleman, it wasn't even your own, and it
turned out it was טבל. Tevel. יין ונמצא יין נסך, Yayin V'nimtza
Yayin Nesech, or wine it turned out to be יין נסך. Yayin
Nesech. So all these things are אסור בהנאה. Asur B'hana'ah. Okay, so
it's so therefore you couldn't have taken any money for them anyway.
So מה שאכלו אכלו Ma She'achlu Achlu what the people ate they
ate, יחזיר להם את הדמים Yachzir Lahem Et HaDamim give them their
money back, it's all אסור בהנאה Asur B'hana'ah for everything. רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar Omer דברים שנפש קצה בהן,
Devarim SheNefesh Katza Bahen, things that people would be disgusted about if
they found out that that was the meat they were eating, יחזיר
להם את הדמים, Yachzir Lahem Et HaDamim, that you give them back
their full money. Because they never would have wanted the stuff to
begin with. If they would have realized they were eating, let's say
טריפה, treifa, even though it tastes the same as non-טריפה, treifa, but
you know, psychologically, like there's actually discussion in the גמרא, Gemara a
גמרא Gemara about like, you know, in כשרות Kashrus about things that
are that that people are disgusted with, do we assume that it
creates טעם לפגם? ta'am lifgam? Like a cockroach falls into your frying
pan, right? Do we say, now, you know, normally if a piece
of חזיר chazir did it, it would be a problem, it's טריפה.
treifa. Well, a cockroach is also טריפה. treifa. But do we say,
no, cockroach, definitely the taste is bad because you're disgusted with the
cockroach? And the way one, so what's the question then? So one
of the ראשונים Rishonim explain it is basically, who knows that a
cockroach tastes bad? Have you ever tasted a cockroach? Right? It's just
that we're disgusted with the thought of it. So is that enough
to make it a טעם לפגם ta'am lifgam case in כשרות? Kashrus?
So here too, that's what רבי יוסי is saying. You might have
eaten some delicious steaks, but then you'll find out that it was
a טריפה treifa and אח, ach, I would have never eaten a
טריפה treifa and you're so disgusted with the thought that you never
would have wanted to eat it, so therefore you get all your
money back. It was a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. However, ושאינה נפש
קצה בהן, veshe'eina nefesh katza bahen, if it's something you're not disgusted
with the thought of, then ינכה להם את דמיהן, yenakeh lahem et
dmeihen, then you have to, then you don't, you give, right, give
a discount. Okay, so you don't give it, you, meaning they did
get some benefit out of it, they ate from it even though
it turned out to be טריפה treifa and even though you weren't
entitled. Now the question is, okay, but you weren't entitled to take
the money, it was אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ואלו הן דברים שנפש קצה בהן, ve'elu hen devarim shenefesh katza bahen,
these are the things that you're disgusted with: נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים.
neveilot utreifot shekatzim uremashim. So there you go, שקצים ורמשים shekatzim uremashim
are like cockroaches or rodents, and נבילות וטריפות, neveilot utreifot, נבילה neveila
is an animal died on its own, טריפה treifa is a טריפה.
treifa. Again, טריפה treifa is pretty interesting because at least for us,
we're not disgusted by the idea of a טריפה, treifa, I don't
think, it had a hole in the womb, in the in the
lung, right? נבילה neveila maybe we would, oh, the animal just died
naturally out of old age. Okay, anyway, those types of things, the,
you know, they never would have wanted and you give them back
their full money. ואלו הן דברים שאין נפש קצה בהן, ve'elu hen
devarim she'ein nefesh katza bahen, the following things are the things you're
not repulsed by: בכורות, a בכור, bechor הלכתית halachically it's forbidden, but
it's a normally kosher meat in terms of all other criteria. טבלים,
tevalim, right, things that תרומות ומעשרות terumot uma'asrot weren't taken from, again,
totally normal fruit and grain. ויין נסך, veyayin nesech, and wine. All
these things have הלכתי halachic statuses, but they're not physically different and
therefore you're not disgusted by it. So now the גמרא Gemara. says,
okay, so maybe they got some benefit and, you know, and whatever,
and they're not totally disgusted by what happened, but how can you
take money?
These are אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
The גמרא says בכור ולימא ליה מאי אפסדתיך, bechor uleima lei mai
afsadetich, why don't you say back to them, why didn't I cause
you a loss?
You weren't allowed to get any benefit anyway. What was the question?
That I understand that I got some benefit from having eaten your
בכור bechor meat, okay, because I'm not disgusted by the whole experience
and every time I think about it, it makes me want to
shudder.
No, actually it says, oh, that
was a delicious steak, too bad it was אסור, assur, good thing
I didn't know.
Okay, so therefore, so therefore I got some benefit, so I I
don't have to pay you full, but there's some, I
pay you some discounted rate.
גמרא says, it's very nice that I got benefit, but it was
אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. You wouldn't have been allowed to get any
benefit from it, so why can you take any of my money?
Okay, so בכור לימא ליה, bechor leima lei, why can't I say
to you, מאי אפסדתיך, mai afsadetich, what did I make you lose
by taking your בכור? bechor It was אסור assur anyway. לא צריכא,
lo tzricha, you need it, דזבין ליה ממקום מום, dezavin lei mimkom
mum, that Michael sold it to me in the place where there
was the blemish, and it would have been possible theoretically to have
gotten a ruling on that blemish even after it was שחט. shechted.
And therefore Michael says to me, דאמר ליה אי לאו דאכלת, de'amar
lei ee lav de'achalt, if you hadn't eaten that, so הוה מחזינא
ליה ושרו ליה עלי, hava machzeina lei vesharu lei alai, I could
have shown it to a חכם and it could have been מתיר
to me. So therefore, yes, it's not definitely that it was אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it might have been מותר, mutar, I needed a
ruling, and you stole from me the opportunity, and it wasn't your
fault, okay, I sold you the meat, but because of you, I
lost the opportunity to perhaps get this to be okay. So that
was some real opportunity cost to me, and therefore I'm allowed to
still get some money from you based on the transaction. Okay, so
that's that case, that in that one case. כרבי יהודה, kerabbi yehuda,
and like רבי יהודה that says you can rule on a בכור
bechor after it's been שחט. shechted. טבלים, tevalim, what if it was
טבל? tevel? Why, you can't benefit from טבל? tevel? No, there's another
obvious answer. הוה מתקנינא ליה ואכילנא ליה, hava metakneina lei ve'achilna lei,
Michael could say, I would have been מפריש, mafrish, I would have
been מפריש תרומות ומעשרות. mafrish terumot uma'asrot. It wasn't a loss, I
could have I could have salvaged this situation. So again, maybe you
can't derive benefit, you know, it is אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah in
this current state, but the point is he's still entitled to some
payment because of his loss of opportunity cost. Okay, so יין נסך,
yayin nesech, how about יין נסך? yayin nesech? What could you have
done with that? על ידי תערובת, al yedei ta'arovet, it was the
case where it was intentionally mixed with what's allowed, but the case
was it was already mixed with other wine. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל
היא, verabban shimon ben gamliel hi, excuse me, יין נסך שנפל לבור,
yayin nesech shenafal labor, if wine falls into a pit of other
let's say wine, כולו אסור בהנאה, kulo assur behana'ah, it's all forbidden
because of the mixture. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, verabban shimon ben
gamliel omer, no, ימכר כולו לעובד כוכבים חוץ מדמי יין נסך שבו,
yimacher kulo le'oved kochavim chutz midmei yayin nesech shebo, you can sell
it to the non-Jew, a Jew can't eat it, but you can
sell it to the non-Jew. Ah, you're benefiting from the יין נסך?
yayin nesech? No, you sell it to him minus the amount of
wine that's forbidden wine. So you're only benefiting from the kosher. He
sold that mixture to me, he could have benefited 90% of its
value and therefore he did lose out something of value. So in
those types of cases where Michael lost out something of value where
I actually even knowing what had happened and do not feel completely
repulsed by the whole experience, Michael is entitled to some partial payment
for having given me something and me having benefited from it. But
in this case, I would have thought that you would have differentiated
between how it became טריף. treif. If it was just the knife,
then no one would be... In terms of whether I'm repulsed by
it. Yeah, I agree. Okay, הדרן עלך פסולי המוקדשין. Hadran Alach P'sulei
Hamukdashin. That is the end of that פרק perek and now we
turn on to the פרק perek I know you've all been waiting
for, which is all about what actually מומים mumim look like. And
if you become an expert in this פרק, perek, you can too
you also can be a מומחה after you get your יורה יורה
and ידין ידין. yadin yadin. Yes, Dov, you wanted to say something?
I guess only the modern reason would be, you know, the idea
that שקץ ולא עשו הם shekatz v'lo asu hem are נפש קצה
בהם nefesh katzbahem is a that's a cultural thing. Right, that's what
I was saying before. Yeah, I mean insectivores and this whole thing.
Yeah, I'm sure, but still for most people it is still נפש
קצה בהם. nefesh katzbahem. Right? How about squirrel? I'm sure squirrel tastes
very lov- very delicious. Rat and squirrel. I mean, that's probably a
majority of the world population
that does eat, you know, that.
Right, that's a very interesting.
Okay, I'm not denying that. That's a people's... Right. Well, not just
Jews, but like Western culture, Western society, Western society, right. Whatever. Right.
Okay. All right, now the מומים. mumim. אלו מומים שוחטין את הבכור.
Elu mumim shochtin es habechor. And the following מומים mumim you can
שחט. shecht. Okay, נפגמה אזנו, nifgama ozno, if there's some damage to
the ear, which sounds like it means like, you know, some... something
is cut. Something is... well, we're going to do cut without missing,
but it sounds like that some... the funny thing is that later
in the משנה mishnah. it talks about that actually it's been pierced,
which actually is a clear removal. This sounds maybe that it's not
like, you know, pierced through and through, but that there's like a
nick in it. Okay, a nick in the skin. נפגמה אזנו nifgama
ozno מן החסחוס או סחסוח, min hachaschus or sachsuch, probably the better
גרסא girsa. is if you look what's the... you have to look
at the bottom of the אלף. aleph. הסחסוח hasachsuch is probably the
right גרסא. It's only from the סחסוח sachsuch אבל לא העור. aval
lo ha'or. Now, but not the skin. What does that mean? So
the סחסוח sachsuch is basically translated as cartilage. I believe what is
the cartilage? It's like this hard... the whole thing is cartilage. Well,
where? No, but it's not the flap. The flap is the עור,
or, but I'm not sure where the cartilage starts. Does it start
with this ridge over here? That's, you know, not just the flappy
stuff. רש"י Rashi sounds like it's more inner, it's more somewhere, you
know, closer to the actual skin itself. So I don't know exactly
where the line is between the flap and the cartilage. I know,
I know. Now, נסדקה nisdeka אף על פי שלא חסרה, af al
pi shelo chasra, if it's cracked even if it's not missing anything.
ניקבה מלא כרשינה, nikva melo karshina, if it has a hole in
it the size of a כרשינה, karshina, which is a certain type
of a, you know, of a lentil bean or something. או שיבשה,
o sheyavesha, or it's dried out. איזו היא יבשה, eizu hi yevesha,
how dry is dry? כל שתינקב ואינה מוציאה דם, kol shetinakev v'eina
motzia dam, if you knit a hole in it and no blood
would come out, so that would be an example of the ear
having dried out. It must be some condition, I don't know how
it happens. רבי יוסי בן משולם אומר Rabbi Yosi ben Meshullam omer
יבשה שתהא נפרכת. yevesha shetehei nifrechet. No, even drier, that if you
basically would like rub it in your hands, it would crumble. So
there's got to be some condition that causes lack of blood flow,
I assume. Now, an interesting point here is you might notice that
some of these things are similar to פסולים psulim of לולב lulav
and אתרוג. esrog. יבש, yavesh, נסדק nisdak by a אתרוג, esrog, right,
חסר כל שהוא, chaser kol shehu, נקב nekev and so on, to
the point that... so I don't know if it served as a
model for חז"ל, Chazal, but to the point that when there's a
question how dry does a לולב lulav have to be to be
יבש, yavesh, some ראשונים Rishonim apply this משנה. mishnah Not that blood
doesn't come out, but the other position in the משנה mishna about
whether it would crumble when you touched it. So it is interesting
to think about that parallel. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. אמאי, Amai, why have we expanded the בכור bechor, to the
מום mum, to include all of these things? פיסח ועיוור כתיב, pise'ach
v'iver ksiv, it says if it is lame or blind. Now, what's
the פסוק? pasuk? The פסוק pasuk is וכי יהיה בו מום פיסח
או עיוור, v'chi yiheyeh bo mum pise'ach o iver, if it has
a blemish, whether it's blind or lame, לא תזבחנו לה' אלהיך. lo
tizbachenu l'Hashem Elokecha. כל מום רע, kol mum ra, thank you, any
bad blemish, לא תזבחנו לה', lo tizbachenu l'Hashem, don't bring it as
a קרבן, korban, בשעריך תאכלנו, bish'arecha tochlennu, eat it in your gates.
So there it tells you, if you've got a מום, mum even
without redeeming it, eat it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay,
but the specific thing it mentions is blind or lame. So let's
say, so maybe it should be limited to that? No, כתיב נמי
כי יהיה בו מום, ksiv nami ki yiheyeh bo mum, it says
a general principle, כי יהיה בו מום. ki yiheyeh bo mum. ואימא
כי יהיה בו מום כלל, v'eima ki yiheyeh bo mum klal, that's
a general statement, פיסח ואו עיוור פרט, pise'ach v'o iver prat, lame
or blind is a specific. כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, if you have
a general and specific you go only by the specific. פיסח ועיוור
אין, מידי אחריני לא, pise'ach v'iver in, midi achrini lo, only blind
and lame, not other things. No, כל מום רע, kol mum ra,
then it says... any bad blemish. חזר וכלל, chazar ve'chalal, so then
it is a more general statement. כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'khlal,
general, specific, general.
אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט, i attah dan ella k'ein haprat,
you generalize from the specific examples. מה פרט מפורש מום שבגלוי ואינו
חוזר, mah prat meforash mum she'bagaluy ve'eino chozer, the same way blind
and lame are things that are on the outside, exposed, visible, number
one, and number two, do not heal. אף כל מום שבגלוי ואינו
חוזר. af kol mum she'bagaluy ve'eino chozer. So we'll apply it to
any blemish which is visible and doesn't heal. So the Gemara says
wait a minute. Okay, well, okay, that one I do. Anyway, the
Gemara says wait a minute, that maybe too broad. ואימה מה פרט
מפורש מום שבגלוי ובוטל ממלאכתו. ve'eima mah prat meforash mum she'bagaluy u'vatel
mi'melachto. Blind and lame is not just an aesthetic; blind and lame
is a real profound problem, it can't do its מלאכה melacha if
it's blind or lame. So maybe only a blemish of that degree?
ואינו חוזר, ve'eino chozer, and it can't be healed. אף כל מום
שבגלוי ובוטל ממלאכתו ואינו חוזר. af kol mum she'bagaluy u'vatel mi'melachto ve'eino
chozer. So why don't I add the criteria that it has to
be such a big מום mum that it's not just aesthetics, but
it can't actually be put to work. אלמה תנן, alama tenan, נפגמה
אזנו מן הסחוס, nifgema ozno min hasachus, ולא מן העור. ve'lo min
ha'or. Why do we say even on the ear, which is a
pure aesthetic thing? It has nothing to do with its ability to
work. So the Gemara says no. כל מום רע, kol mum ra,
ריבוייא הוא. ribuyya hu. Like Michael said, we don't always do כלל
ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'khlal, sometimes we do ריבוי, ribuy, which is
more inclusive. And even if in general we would do כלל ופרט
וכלל, klal u'prat u'khlal, כל מום רע, kol mum ra, any bad
מום mum? is coming to tell you to interpret it more broadly.
So more broadly tells us even not something that really affects its
usability, but even something that's just at the aesthetic level. So the
Gemara says okay, but if you're going to be that broad, אי
הכי, i hachi, if you say that, so מומים שבסתר נמי, mumim
she'baseter nami, maybe even if it's not visible? Maybe we should be
as expansive as possible. אלמה תנן, alama tenan, why did we teach:
חוטין החיצונות, chutin hachitzonot, if you have the incisors, שנפגמו, she'nifgemu, that
they were a little bit chipped, או שנגממו, o she'nigmemu, or they
were sort of cracked, והפנימיות, ve'hapnimiyot, and the molars, שנעקרו, she'ne'ekru, if
they were completely fell out. And now the molars have to completely
come out. Why? Because since it's harder to see them, you won't
see it if they're a small blemish. You'll only see it if
the molar is completely missing. So that's evidence that if it's something
that's not visible, it's not a problem. So why is that? So
the Gemara says: נעקרו אין נפגמו ונגממו לא. ne'ekru in nifgemu ve'nigmemu
lo. So by the molars, it's only if they're completely torn out,
not if it's just chipped or cracked. Why is that? It's because
they are not visible. And so why do we have a criteria
of visible? So the Gemara says no. בעינן מום רע וליכא. ba'inan
mum ra ve'leka. It says כל מום רע. kol mum ra. It
has to be bad. So bad means, and again, this is all
from the human perspective; nobody asked the animal. So from where we
stand, if it's not something that actually affects its usability, the only
other way it's bad is from an aesthetic perspective. So something that
is not even an aesthetic problem, it's not visible, that's not a
מום רע. mum ra. Of course, it does make you wonder about,
have we completely defined things in terms of aesthetics? Let's say it
was an inner problem and non-visible, but it still affected its usability?
Presumably we have redefined it as being about aesthetics and not at
all about being its functionality. Could we say just an ugly looking
animal? Would you say that's a מום? mum, Right. So no, I
mean, there's a concept of a blemish which is some deformity. But
yes, it's not purely a like זה קלי ואנווהו zeh keli ve'anvehu
concept. So now the Gemara says like this: אי הכי מום עובר
נמי. i hachi mum oveir nami. Okay, but why do you exclude
a transitory blemish? That's also bad. אלמה תנן, alama tenan, why do
we teach: ולא מן העור, ve'lo min ha'or, not the flap of
the ear? Presumably the difference of the flap is that the flap
will heal, and the cartilage will not. So the Gemara says: מום
עובר סברא הוא. mum oveir sevara hu. That's just logic. השתא מפרק
לא פרקינן עלויה משחט שחטינן עלויה? hashta mifrak lo farkinan aluyeh mish-chat
shachtinan aluyeh? The Gemara says: if it is a transitory blemish, you're
not allowed to redeem it. A קרבן korban with a מום, mum,
you redeem and you use the money to buy another קרבן. korban.
But if it's a transitory, if it doesn't have a מום, mum,
you can't redeem. Even if it has a transitory מום, mum you
can't redeem. So if a transitory מום mum, by other קרבנות korbanot
is not enough to change their status to allow you to redeem,
how could it be powerful enough to allow you to eat this
בכור bechor out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? We keep on
go back to that, that a בכור bechor is a huge חידוש.
chiddush. With a blemish, you don't have to redeem it; you eat
it out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So to have that
power for a transitory מום, mum if by other animals it won't
even allow you to redeem, that can't be. How do we know
that's true about other animals? דתניא, de'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא:
braisa: ואם כל בהמה טמאה אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן להשם. ve'im
kol behemah tmeiah asher lo yakrivu mimenah korban la'Hashem. If it's a
non-kosher animal that you can't bring as a קרבן, korban, then it
says: ופדה בערכך, u'fadah be'erkecha, you redeem. So the ברייתא braisa says:
בבעלי מומים הכתוב מדבר. be'ba'alei mumim hakatuv medabeir. It doesn't literally mean
non-kosher like a חזיר. chazir. It means something that can't be brought
as a קרבן, korban, אשר לא תקריב ממנה. asher lo takriv mimenah.
It has a blemish, and therefore you redeem it. אתה אומר בבעלי
מומים שנפדו הכתוב מדבר, attah omer be'ba'alei mumim she'nifdu hakatuv medabeir, you're
telling me that it's talking about a קרבן korban that was redeemed,
or therefore it has to be redeemed because it has a blemish,
או אינו אלא בבהמה טמאה. o eino ella be'behemah tmeiah. Maybe it's
really talking ממש, mamash, maybe it's really talking about an only non-kosher
animal you redeem, not an animal with a blemish. כשהוא אומר ואם
בבהמה הטמאה, K'shehu omer ve'im bahema hatme'ah, of that it says explicitly
non-kosher. הרי בהמה טמאה אמור. Harei behema tme'ah amur. That says explicitly.
מה אני מקיים אשר לא יקריב ממנו, Ma ani mekayem asher lo
yakriv mimenu, why does it have to add that you do not
bring from it a קרבן? korban? הוי אומר זה בעלי מומים שנפדו.
Hevei omer ze ba'alei mumim shenifdu. That means what? When you say
טמאה? tme'ah? I don't know. So that tells you that it also
includes the case of an animal that was a קרבן korban that
had a blemish and can't be brought because of its blemish, therefore
what do you do? You redeem it. יכול יפדו על מום עובר,
Yachol yifdu al mum over, maybe you can even redeem it if
it's a transitory blemish? Again, not a בכור, בכור can't be redeemed,
but another קרבן. korban. תלמוד לומר אשר לא יקריבו ממנו קרבן להשם.
Talmud lomar asher lo yakrivu mimenu korban l'Hashem. Cannot be brought from
it a קרבן, korban, meaning never brought from it a קרבן. korban.
מי שאינו קרב כל עיקר, Mi she'eino karev kol ikar, something that
can never be a קרבן, korban, יצא זה שאינו קרב היום אבל
למחר, yatza ze she'eino karev hayom aval lemachar, to exclude something that
can in the future be brought. So if a transitory מום cannot
be enough to redeem it when you're going to use the money
and transfer the קדושה kedusha and whatever, nevertheless not significant enough to
redeem it, it's certainly not significant enough to give you license to
eat a בכור outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And one final
answer how we know not a transitory blemish, אי בעית אימא, ei
bayit eima, if you want you could say, אם כן פיסח ועיוור
למה לי. im ken pise'ach ve'iver lama li. If we're going to
include everything, so why does the תורה Torah bother giving any example
of פיסח ועיוור? pise'ach ve'iver? There has to be some limit. So
the limit is is that it has to be again visible, or
that actually we learn from the word רע, ra, that it has
to be visible and that it has to be something that is
permanent. And those are the two basic criteria and now we're going
to go through this משנה in the future to explore all of
these examples of these מומים. mumim. Okay, חנוכה שמח. Chanukah same'ach. One
of these days.